Guide to the Caldwell B. Esselstyn Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Other Professional Activities, 1952-1973; Series III; 15' (37 boxes)
  - Group Health Association of America
    - Correspondence and Subject Files
      - Select
        - Fund raising and contributions: correspondence and reports, 1966-1974 June (Box 58, Folder 93)
        - Fund raising and contributions (Group Health Foundation): correspondence, budget and related material, 1974 July-1975 January (Box 58, Folder 94)
        - Genesee Valley Group Health Association: correspondence, brochures and reports, 1973-1975 (Box 58, Folder 95)
        - Group Health Association, Inc. (Washington, D.C.): correspondence, budgets and reports, 1965-1967 (Box 59, Folder 96)
        - Hansen, Horace R.
          - Correspondence and reprints, 1958-1962 (Box 59, Folder 97)
          - State medical licensure laws survey, 1962 (Box 59, Folder 98)
        - Health Insurance Benefits Advisory Council (Box 59, Folder 98)
          See: box 11, folder 256
        - Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York (Box 59, Folder 98)
        - Health Maintenance Organization Services (Box 59, Folder 98)
        - Kerr, Lorin E.: correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 59, Folder 99)
        - Krantz, Goldie: correspondence, 1964 (Box 59, Folder 100)
        - Legislation: correspondence, news clippings and reprints, 1950-1964 (Box 59, Folder 101)
        - Lichtenberg, Henry H.: correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 59, Folder 102)
        - Local 88, Meat and Related Industries Welfare Fund Trust: report, 1964 December (Box 59, Folder 103)
        - McCaffee, Kenneth M.: correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 59, Folder 104)
        - Medical Foundation of Bellaire: correspondence, petitions and press releases, 1963-1966 (Box 59, Folder 105)
        - Medicare
          - Legislation, reports and testimony, 1965 (Box 59, Folder 106)
          - Correspondence, memoranda and photographs, 1965-1967 (Box 59, Folder 107)
        - Metropolitan Health Council (Indianapolis): correspondence, programs and reprints, 1973-1974 (Box 59, Folder 108)
        - Moorehead, Mildred: correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box 60, Folder 109)
        - Mott, Frederick D.: correspondence, 1965 (Box 60, Folder 110)
        - New Jersey Group Health Insurance vs. Charles R. Howell: affidavit and correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 60, Folder 111)
        - Physicians Forum: correspondence, 1961 August (Box 60, Folder 112)
        - Public relations and advertising: correspondence, 1960-1964 (Box 60, Folder 113)
        - Research project: application and correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box 60, Folder 114)
        - Saskatchewan group practice development
          - Correspondence, legislation and reports, 1962 June-July (Box 60, Folder 115)
          - Correspondence and notes, 1962 August (Box 60, Folder 116)
          - Correspondence and reports, 1962 August-Dec, 1963-1964 (Box 60, Folder 117-118)
        - Segadelli, Louis J.: correspondence and copies of legislation, 1965-1968 (Box 60, Folder 119)
        - Staten Island voluntary hospitals and H.I.P. physicians: correspondence, 1960 (Box 60, Folder 120)
        - United Housing Project (A. E. Kazen): correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box 60, Folder 121)
        - United States Department of Health, Education and Welfare, Conference on Medical Costs (Box 60, Folder 121)
          See: box 18, folders 453-454
        - United States Department of Health, Education and Welfare, Public Health Service, Feasibility Study: correspondence and background material, 1967 (Box 60, Folder 122)
        - Van Goor, Robert: correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box 60, Folder 123)
    - Subdivisions
      - Annual meeting
        - Proceedings, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 124)
        - Correspondence, agenda and related material, 1962 (Box 60, Folder 125)
        - Notes, 1963 (Box 61, Folder 126)
        - Minutes, 1966 (Box 61, Folder 127)
        - Correspondence, agenda and reports, 1968 (Box 61, Folder 128)
        - Reports, 1969 (Box 61, Folder 129)
        - Reports, resolutions and related material, 1974 (Box 61, Folder 130)
      - Awards Committee: correspondence, text of remarks and reprints, 1968-1971, 1974 (Box 61, Folder 131)
      - Board of Directors and Executive Committee
        - Correspondence, minutes and related material, 1959-1963 (Box 61, Folder 132-136)
        - Correspondence, minutes and related material, 1964-1973 May-December (Box 62, Folder 137-144)
        - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 62, Folder 145)
      - Book Committee
        - Correspondence, notes and outlines, 1959-1960 (Box 63, Folder 146)
        - Correspondence, minutes and drafts of chapters, 1961 (Box 63, Folder 147)
        - Drafts of chapters, 1961-1963 (Box 63, Folder 148)
        - Correspondence and drafts of chapters, 1962 (Box 63, Folder 149)
        - Correspondence, 1963-1965 (Box 63, Folder 150)
        - [Draft of text?], Circa 1964 (Box 63, Folder 151)
      - Committee on Labor Participation: memorandum, 1964 (Box 63, Folder 152)
      - Drug Formulary Committee: correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 63, Folder 153)
      - Group Practice Prepayment Plan Operations Committee: correspondence, memoranda and reports, 1963 (Box 63, Folder 154)
      - Group Practice Prepayment Plan Development Committee
        - Transcript of conference, "Tooling-up for Medicare", 1965 (Box 63, Folder 155)
        - Correspondence, memoranda and related material, 1965-1966 (Box 64, Folder 156)
        - Correspondence, memoranda and related material, 1968 (Box 64, Folder 157)
      - Legislative Committee: correspondence and newsclippings, 1960-1961 (Box 64, Folder 158)
      - Medical Bill of Rights Review Committee: correspondence, 1961 (Box 64, Folder 159)
      - Medical Directors Division
        - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 64, Folder 160)
        - Correspondence, minutes and related material, 1974-1975 (Box 64, Folder 161)
      - Medical Rights Committee
        - Correspondence, minutes and reports, 1963-1964 (Box 64, Folder 162)
        - Correspondence, minutes and legal briefs, 1965-1967 (Box 64, Folder 163)
      - Nominating Committee: correspondence and reports, 1961-1966 (Box 64, Folder 164)
      - Occupational Health Committee: correspondence, 1964 (Box 64, Folder 165)
      - Professional Services Committee
        - Correspondence, programs and reports, 1957-1960 (Box 64, Folder 166)
        - Correspondence and reports, 1961-1963 (Box 65, Folder 167)
      - Search Committee: correspondence, 1974 (Box 65, Folder 168)
      - Speakers Bureau: correspondence and newsclippings, 1973-1974 (Box 65, Folder 169)
      - Standards Committee: correspondence, forms and manual, 1973-1974 (Box 65, Folder 170)
    - Programs and Institutes
      - Group Dental Care and Prepayment: correspondence and program, 1965-1966 (Box 65, Folder 171)
      - Group Health Institute
        - Proceedings, 1953-1954, 1956-1958 (Box 65, Folder 172-175)
        - Correspondence, reports and proceedings, 1960 (Box 65, Folder 176)
        - Correspondence and proceedings, 1961 May 8-10 (Box 65, Folder 177)
        - Correspondence and proceedings, 1962-1965 (Box 66, Folder 178-179)
        - Correspondence, committee reports and minutes, 1966-1967 (Box 66, Folder 180)
        - Minutes and proceedings, 1968 (Box 66, Folder 181)
        - Proceedings, 1972 (Box 66, Folder 182)
        - Correspondence, proceedings and related material, 1973 (Box 66, Folder 183)
        - Correspondence, proceedings and related material, 1974 (Box 66, Folder 184)
      - Medical Care Research Meeting: correspondence and summary, 1961 (Box 66, Folder 185)
      - National Conference on Private Health Insurance: agenda and mss., 1967 (Box 67, Folder 186)
      - Prepaid Group Practice Teach-In: correspondence, 1971 (Box 67, Folder 187)
      - Rural Health Maintenance Organization Conference: correspondence, program and related material, 1974 (Box 67, Folder 188)
      - White House Conference on Aging: correspondence and conference material, 1960-1961 (Box 67, Folder 189)
      - Reference
        - Speeches and writings by others, 1961-1968 (Box 67, Folder 190)
        - Pamphlets, 1962-1967, undated (Box 67, Folder 191)
        - Reprints, 1967-1974 (Box 67, Folder 192)
        - Legislation, "Health Maintenance Organization Act", 1973 (Box 67, Folder 193)
        - Publications, 1959-1974 (Box 67, Folder 194)
  - Health Insurance Benefits Advisory Council
    - General Papers
      - Background book, 1965 (Box 67, Folder 195)
      - Correspondence, memoranda and membership lists, 1965-1966 (Box 68, Folder 196)
      - Consultants' meetings book, 1965 September - 1966 June (Box 68, Folder 197)
      - Approved minutes, 1965 November - 1966 March 26 (Box 68, Folder 198)
      - Agenda book, 1965 December 17-19 (Box 68, Folder 199)
      - Correspondence, memoranda and reports, 1965-1968 (Box 68, Folder 200)
      - Agenda book, 1966 January 7-9, 1966 January 28-30, 1966 February 25-27, 1966 March 26-27, 1966 April 30-May 1 (Box 69, Folder 201-205)
      - Approved minutes, 1966 April -1967 (Box 70, Folder 206)
      - Agenda book, 1966 July 30-31, 1966 September 10-11 (Box 70, Folder 207-208)
      - Correspondence, memoranda, and regulations, 1966 September-December (Box 70, Folder 209)
      - Agenda book, 1966 November 5-6, 1966 December 9-11 (Box 70, Folder 210-211)
      - Presidential meeting on medicare implementation, 1966 (Box 71, Folder 212)
      - New members' background book, part I, 1966-1968 (Box 71, Folder 213-214)
      - New members' background book, part II, 1966-1967 (Box 71, Folder 215)
      - Agenda book, 1967 January 7-8 (Box 72, Folder 216)
      - Agenda book (part 1), 1967 March 4 (Box 72, Folder 217)
      - Agenda book (part 2), 1967 March 4 (Box 72, Folder 218)
      - Approved minutes, 1967 March-September (Box 72, Folder 219)
      - Reports on the administration of the program and the results of contract performance reviews, 1967 June (Box 72, Folder 220)
      - Agenda book, 1967 June 3-4, 1967 September 16-17 (Box 72, Folder 221-222)
      - Agenda book, 1967 (Box 73, Folder 223)
      - Correspondence, print material and reports re: Medicare components and amendments, 1967 (Box 73, Folder 224)
      - Reports and studies re: effects of health legislation, 1967-1968 (Box 73, Folder 225)
      - Agenda book, 1968 March 2-3, 1968 April 27-28, 1968 June 29 (Box 73, Folder 226-228)
      - Report and correspondence, Task Force on Medical Services, 1968 August (Box 74, Folder 229)
      - Report, Committee on Medical Services, 1968 (Box 74, Folder 230)
      - Correspondence, print material and reports re: Medicare components and amendments, 1968 (Box 74, Folder 231)
      - Photographs and slides, 1968, undated (Box 74, Folder 232)
      - Correspondence, annual report and membership lists, 1969-1971 (Box 74, Folder 233)
      - American Medical Association (Box 74, Folder 233)
      - Ball, Robert (Box 74, Folder 233)
        See: box 12, folder 275
      - Community Health Association: (Box 74, Folder 233)
      - Cornelius, Dorothy (Box 74, Folder 233)
        See: box 12, folder 304
      - Gordon, Kermit (Box 74, Folder 233)
        See: box 13, folder 326
      - Nelson, Russell A. (Box 74, Folder 233)
    - Procedural Manuals and Circulars
      - Group Practice Prepayment Plan Letters, 1968, 1973 (Box 74, Folder 234)
      - Intermediary agreement pursuant to section 1816, 1967 (Box 74, Folder 235)
      - Intermediary Letters, 1967-1968 (Box 75, Folder 236)
      - Intermediary manuals, 1967 (Box 75, Folder 237)
      - Intermediary manual revisions (part A), 1967 August - 1968 February (Box 75, Folder 238)
      - Intermediary manual revisions (part A), 1968 March August (Box 75, Folder 239)
      - Intermediary manual revisions (part B), 1967-1968 (Box 75, Folder 240)
      - Staff memoranda
        - Administrative agents, parts A and B, designation and functions, 1967 (Box 75, Folder 241)
        - Admission procedures, [1967?] (Box 75, Folder 242)
      - Conditions for coverage of services of independent labs, 1967 (Box 76, Folder 243)
      - Conditions of participation for hospitals, 1965-1967 (Box 76, Folder 244)
      - Conditions of participation for extended care facilities, 1966-1967 (Box 76, Folder 245-247)
      - Disclosure of information, 1967 (Box 76, Folder 248)
      - Implementation and operation, 1966-1967 (Box 76, Folder 249)
      - Outpatient services, 1966 (Box 77, Folder 250)
      - Physician certification and recertification, 1966-1967 (Box 77, Folder 251)
      - Physicians and physicians' services, 1966-1967 (Box 77, Folder 252)
      - Provider services manuals and regulations, 1968 (Box 77, Folder 253)
      - Reasonable charges, 1966-1967 (Box 77, Folder 254)
      - Reimbursement, hospital based physicians, 1966-1967 (Box 77, Folder 255)
      - Reimbursement, group practice plans, 1965-1967 (Box 77, Folder 256)
      - Reimbursement for hospitals and other institutions, 1965-1966 (Box 77, Folder 257)
      - Reimbursement for provider costs, 1966-1967 (Box 77, Folder 258)
      - Utilization review, 1965-1967 (Box 77, Folder 259)
    - Miscellaneous Print Material
      - Reprints and news releases, 1965-1968 (Box 77, Folder 260)
      - Manuscript (Charles G. Child), 1966 (Box 78, Folder 261)
      - Social Security Amendments of 1967, H.R. 5710
        - Testimony transcripts, 1967 March (Box 78, Folder 262-263)
        - Commissioner's Bulletins, 1967 (Box 78, Folder 264)
        - Correspondence, reports and summaries, 1967 (Box 78, Folder 265)
        - Medicare Guidebook (amended), 1967 (Box 78, Folder 266)
  - Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York, Inc.
    - Correspondence
      - General correspondence and testimony, 1969 (Box 78, Folder 267)
      - Baehr, George, 1954-1963 (Box 78, Folder 268)
      - Barr, David, 1960-1961 (Box 78, Folder 269)
      - Bigel, Jack (Box 78, Folder 269)
      - Brindle, James, 1962 (Box 78, Folder 270)
      - Daily, Edwin, 1961 (Box 78, Folder 271)
      - Group Health Association of America (Box 78, Folder 271)
        See: box 5, folder 120
      - New York City Department of Health (Box 78, Folder 271)
        See: box 16, folder 399
      - New York State Department of Health, Bureau of Emergency Medical Services (Box 78, Folder 271)
        See: box 47, folders 375-384
    - Board of Directors
      - Minutes, memoranda and reports, 1960-1964 May-Jan, 1964 October-December (Box 78, Folder 272-275)
      - Minutes, memoranda and reports, 1965 January-Jul, 1965 September-1967 June (Box 79, Folder 276-286)
      - Minutes, memoranda and reports, 1967 July-1968 Aug, 1970-1971 May, 1971 September-Nov, 1972 January-Oct, 1973 (Box 80, Folder 287-297)
      - Minutes, memoranda and reports, 1974 January-October (Box 81, Folder 298-299)
    - Annual Members Meeting: annual report, photographs and notes, 1974 May 14 (Box 81, Folder 300)
    - "The Emerging Role of Consumers in the Health Delivery System": program and correspondence, 1974 (Box 81, Folder 301)
    - Reference
      - "Bulletins", 1956, 1958 (Box 81, Folder 302)
      - Reports, 1956-1961 (Box 81, Folder 303-304)
      - Reports, 1962-1963 (Box 81, Folder 305)
        See also: box 23, folders 36-46
  - New York State Public Health Council
    - General Papers
      - Correspondence, press releases, reprints, 1955-1957 (Box 81, Folder 306)
      - Correspondence, reports, 1958-1959 (Box 81, Folder 307-309)
      - Correspondence, press releases, 1960-1961 (Box 81, Folder 310-311)
      - Correspondence, reprints, 1962-1963 (Box 81, Folder 312)
      - Correspondence, press releases, 1964, 1967 (Box 81, Folder 313-314)
    - Meeting Files
      - Background material, 1961 Jan, 1961 Mar, 1961 Apr, 1961 June (Box 82, Folder 315-318)
      - Background material, 1961 Sep, 1961 October, 1961 Dec, 1962 Jan, 1962 Mar, 1962 Apr, 1962 Jun, 1962 Sep, 1962 October (Box 83, Folder 319-327)
      - Background material, 1962 December-1968 (Box 84, Folder 328-330)
  - Physician's Committee for Health Care for the Aged through Social Security
    - Background Material
      - Correspondence re: "Cooperative Clinic Bill, S. 1667", 1957 (Box 84, Folder 331)
      - Correspondence and statements re: legislation, 1957-1958 (Box 84, Folder 332)
      - Correspondence and statements re: Forand bill, 1957-1959 Oct, 1960 January-April (Box 84, Folder 333-336)
      - Newsletters and pamphlets, 1958-1960 (Box 84, Folder 337)
      - Correspondence and statements re: New York and Ohio state legislation, 1959-1960 (Box 85, Folder 338)
      - Correspondence, statements and print material re: miscellaneous legislation, 1960 (Box 85, Folder 339-340)
    - General Papers
      - Correspondence, statements and reports, 1961 January-February 23 (Box 85, Folder 341)
      - Correspondence and reports, 1961 February 24-March (Box 85, Folder 342)
      - Correspondence, statements and print material, 1961 April-Sep, 1962 January-May (Box 85, Folder 343-348)
      - Correspondence and T.V. transcript, "Medical Care Dispute", 1962 May (Box 86, Folder 349)
      - Correspondence, statements and print material, 1962 June-July (Box 86, Folder 350-351)
      - Correspondence, releases and print material, 1963 January-May (Box 86, Folder 352)
      - Correspondence, statements and reports, 1963 June-July (Box 86, Folder 353)
      - Correspondence and leaflets, 1963 August-September (Box 86, Folder 354)
      - Correspondence and statements, 1963 October-December (Box 86, Folder 355-356)
      - Correspondence, statements, print material and photograph, 1964 January (Box 86, Folder 357)
      - Correspondence, statements, reports and print material, 1964 February-May (Box 86, Folder 358)
      - Reports and print material, 1964 June-July (Box 86, Folder 359)
      - Correspondence and statements, 1964 August (Box 86, Folder 360)
      - Correspondence, statements and T.V. transcript, "Rx for a Nightmare", 1964 September-December (Box 87, Folder 361)
      - T.V. transcript, "Medicare is Needed Now", 1965 June (Box 87, Folder 362)
      - Correspondence and reports, 1965-1966 (Box 87, Folder 363)
      - Oral history interview transcript, 1966 (Box 87, Folder 364)
      - Ball, Robert (Box 87, Folder 364)
      - Roemer, Milton (Box 87, Folder 364)
  - Public Affairs Committee, Inc., Health Advisory Committee
    - Correspondence and reports, 1959-1964 (Box 87, Folder 365)
    - Correspondence and drafts of articles, 1965-1967 (Box 87, Folder 366-367)
    - Correspondence and drafts of articles, 1967 (Box 87, Folder 367)
    - Correspondence and reports, 1968 (Box 87, Folder 368)
    - Correspondence, reports and drafts of articles, 1970-1971 (Box 87, Folder 369)
    - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 87, Folder 370)
- Writings, 1949-1974; Series IV; 1' (3 boxes)
  WRITINGS is organized chronologically.
  - Correspondence, speech texts, 1949-1952 (Box 88, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence, reprint, 1953 (Box 88, Folder 3)
  - Notes, draft, 1954 (Box 88, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, tear sheet, 1954 (Box 88, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, drafts, 1955 (Box 88, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, speech text, 1956-1957 (Box 88, Folder 7-8)
  - Correspondence, notes, speech texts, 1958-1960 March (Box 88, Folder 9-11)
  - Correspondence, speech texts, 1960 April-June (Box 88, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, reprints, speech texts, 1960 July-September (Box 88, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, notes, reprints, speech texts, 1960 October-Dec, undated (Box 88, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, reprints, speech texts, 1961-1962 April (Box 89, Folder 15-17)
  - Correspondence, notes, speech texts, 1962 May-Dec, undated (Box 89, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, reprints, speech texts, 1963 January-June (Box 89, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, notes, reprints, speech texts, 1963 July-Dec, undated (Box 89, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, reprints, speech texts, 1964 January-March (Box 89, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, notes, reprints, speech texts, 1964 April-1965 (Box 90, Folder 22-23)
  - Correspondence, notes, speech texts, 1966 (Box 90, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, notes, speech texts, reprints, 1967 (Box 90, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, reprints and speech texts, 1968 (Box 90, Folder 26)
  - Speech texts, 1969 (Box 90, Folder 27)
  - Notes, speech texts and tear sheets, 1970 (Box 90, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, notes and speech texts, 1971 (Box 90, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, notes, reprints and speech texts, 1972-1973 (Box 91, Folder 30-31)
  - Speech texts and reprints, 1974 (Box 91, Folder 32)
- Reference, 1955-1970; Series V; 3' (6 boxes)
  REFERENCE is organized alphabetically by topic.
  - Aging and Medical Care, 1956-1962 May (Box 91a, Folder 1-3)
  - Aging and Medical Care, 1962 June-1963 (Box 92, Folder 4)
  - Canada, Saskatchewan Doctors Dispute
    - Annual report re: public health, 1960-1961 (Box 92, Folder 5)
    - Annual report re: Saskatchewan Hospital Services Plan, 1960-1961 (Box 92, Folder 6)
    - Annual report and supplement re: Saskatchewan Medical Care Insurance Commission, 1962, 1965-1966 (Box 92, Folder 7)
    - Brief and other material re: Advisory Planning Committee on Medical Care, 1960-1961 (Box 92, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence and copies: Memorandum of Agreement, Government of the Province of Saskatchewan and the College of Physicians and Surgeons of Saskatchewan, 1962 (Box 92, Folder 9)
    - Fee schedule re: College of Physicians and Surgeons of Saskatchewan, 1960 (Box 92, Folder 10)
    - Legislation, 1953-1962 (Box 92, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous newsletters, 1962 (Box 92, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous reports and print material, 1959, 1961-1962 (Box 93, Folder 13)
    - Newsclippings and "Public Voice for Medical Insurance", 1962 April-August (Box 93, Folder 14)
    - Report re: Saskatchewan Hospital Survey and Master Plan, 1962 (Box 93, Folder 15)
    - Speeches by Saskatchewan Premier W. S. Lloyd and notes on Lord Taylor's speech, 1962 May-August (Box 93, Folder 16)
    - Speeches presented to Medical Care Section and G.H.A.A., 90th Annual Meeting of A.P.H.A., 1962 October 17 (Box 93, Folder 17)
  - Desk diaries and pocket calendars, 1950-1953 (Box 93, Folder 18-19)
  - Desk diaries and pocket calendars, 1954-1960 (Box 94, Folder 20-24)
  - Desk diaries and pocket calendars, 1961-1963 (Box 95, Folder 25-27)
  - Labor and health care, 1953-1974 (Box 95, Folder 28-30)
  - Labor and health care, 1958-1967 (Box 96, Folder 31-33)
  - Rip Van Winkle Foundation: panel discussion, dictaphone belts, 1956 (Box 96, Folder 34-39)